Guide to the Gilbert A. Harrison Papers Relating to Thornton Wilder
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gilbert A. Harrison papers relating to Thornton Wilder
1939-1975
YCAL MSS 372
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.72
(21 boxes)
The collection contains research files, interviews, correspondence, writings, and other materials relating to Gilbert A. Harrison's biography of Thornton Wilder, The Enthusiast: A Life of Thornton Wilder (New Haven: Ticknor & Fields, 1983). Harrison's research files, which include notes, photocopies of correspondence and writings, and clippings, make up the bulk of the collection. In addition to the research files, the collection includes: sound recordings of interviews with members of the Wilder family and others, such as Alfred Hitchcock and Lillian Gish; correspondence with Wilder family, scholars, and publishers; a corrected draft of the biography and reviews; and other materials, including biographical information, a copy of Wilder's will, and reference photographs.
Harrison, Gilbert A.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Gilbert A. Harrison, 1984 and 1985.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 15-16 (sound recordings): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Gilbert A. Harrison (1915-2008)
Gilbert A. Harrison was born in Detroit on May 18, 1915, one of three children to Samuel and Mabel Wolfe Harrison. He earned a B.A. degree in psychology from UCLA in 1937 and went on to serve in the U.S. Army in World War II. Following the war, in 1948, Harrison became national chairman of the American Veterans Committe. In 1953, with his wife, Anne Blaine, he purchased The New Republic, where he served as publisher and editor until 1974. Harrison was the author of two books, A Timeless Affair: The Life of Anita McCormick Blaine (1979), a biography of his grandmother-in-law, and The Enthusiast: A Life of Thornton Wilder (1983), and editor of several others, including Gertrude Stein's America (1965) and The Critic as Artist (1972).
Scope and Contents
The collection contains research files, interviews, correspondence, writings, and other materials relating to Gilbert A. Harrison's biography of Thornton Wilder, The Enthusiast: A Life of Thornton Wilder (1983). Harrison's research files, which include notes, photocopies of correspondence and writings, and clippings, make up the bulk of the collection. In addition to the research files, there are audio recordings of interviews with members of the Wilder family and others, such as Alfred Hitchcock and Lillian Gish, correspondence with Wilder family, scholars, and publishers, a corrected draft of the biography, and reviews. Other materials include biographical information, a copy of Wilder's will, and photographs.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Research Files, 1976-[1983]. II. Interviews, 1979-1981. III. Correspondence, 1956-1985. IV. Writings, 1980-1984. V. Other Papers, 1984.
American drama -- 20th Century; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Biography; Photographic prints; Audiovisual materials; Sound recordings; Biographers; Gish, Lillian, 1893-1993; Harrison, Gilbert A.; Hitchcock, Alfred, 1899-1980; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975; Ticknor and Fields
- Research Files, 1976-[1983]; Series I; 5.63; (14 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically and alphabetically by Harrison's folder headings.
  Scope and Contents
  The bulk of the Gilbert A. Harrison papers consist of research files for Harrison's biography of Thornton Wilder, The Enthusiast: A Life of Thornton Wilder (1983). In addition to Harrison's notes, the research files contain a significant quantity of photocopies of correspondence and writings relating to Wilder, and clippings. Though largely undated, the files most likely date from the earliest interviews and correspondence in 1979 to publication of the biography in 1983.
  - "Early Years", undated; 3 (Box 1)
  - 1915-1919, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - 1915-1919, undated; 2 (Box 2)
  - 1920-1927, undated; 3 (Box 2)
  - 1920-1927, undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - 1928-1929, undated; 3 (Box 3)
  - 1930-1936, undated; 3 (Box 4)
  - "Family and 1937", undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - 1938, undated (Box 4)
  - 1938, undated (Box 5)
  - 1939-1940, undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - 1941-1942, undated; 3 (Box 5)
  - 1943-1947, undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - 1948-1949, undated; 3 (Box 6)
  - 1950-1951, undated (Box 6)
  - 1950-1951, undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - 1952-1954, undated; 3 (Box 7)
  - 1955-1958, undated (Box 7)
  - 1955-1958, undated; 2 (Box 8)
  - 1959-1961, undated (Box 8)
  - 1962-1963, undated; 3 (Box 8)
  - 1964-1965, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - 1966-1967, undated; 3 (Box 9)
  - 1968-1969, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - 1970-1972, undated (Box 10)
  - 1973, undated; 3 (Box 10)
  - 1974-1975, undated; 3 (Box 10)
  - "Beliefs", undated (Box 11)
  - "Charlotte Wilder", undated (Box 11)
  - "Comments & Observations & Chronology", undated (Box 11)
  - ["Counder"?], undated; 3 (Box 11)
  - "Men and Women", undated (Box 11)
  - "Miscellaneous", undated; 7 (Box 12)
  - "Miscellaneous", 1976-1982, undated; 2 (Box 13)
  - "One and the Many...", undated (Box 13)
  - "Personal Characteristics", undated (Box 13)
  - Untitled, undated; 2 (Box 13)
  - Untitled, undated; 2 (Box 14)
- Interviews, 1979-1981; Series II; 0.42; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by audio cassette label heading.
  Series II, Interviews, contains sound recordings of interviews conducted by Harrison with members of the Wilder family and others. Interviewees include Amos Wilder, Isabel Wilder, Janet Wilder Dakin, "Tappy" Wilder, Alfred Hitchcock, Lillian Gish, Malcolm Cowley, and Catherine Coffin.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - A. Alfred Hitchcock Hollywood... B. Samuel Steward, 1980 January (Box 15)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Reference copy available.
  - A. Amos Wilder (Cambridge), 1979-1980; 2 (Box 15)
  - A. Amos and Mrs. Wilder, Cambridge. B. W. J. Lewis, followed by Louise Talma NYC, 1979 (Box 15)
  - A. Amos Wilder and Wife III. B. Amos Wilder and Mrs. Amos Wilder IV, 1979 April 7 (Box 15)
  - A. Cass Camfield... B. Theresa Robinson NYC, 1979 (Box 15)
  - A. Catherine Coffin, undated (Box 15)
  - A. Genee and Bill Fadiman Beverly Hills. B. Isabel Wilder New Haven, 1979 (Box 15)
  - A. Isabel Wilder I N.Y.C. B. Isabel II, 1979 April 5 (Box 15)
  - A. Isabel Wilder I. B. Isabel Wilder II, 1979 May 17 (Box 15)
  - A. Isabel Wilder III. B. Isabel Wilder IV, 1979 May 17 (Box 15)
  - A. Isabel Wilder III. B. Isabel Wilder IV, Catherine Coffin, 1980 January 3 (Box 15)
  - A. Isabel Wilder I. B. Isabel Wilder II, 1980 February 11 (Box 15)
  - A. Isabel Wilder III. B. Isabel Wilder IV, 1980 February 11 (Box 15)
  - A. Isabel Wilder I. B. Isabel Wilder II, 1980 February 18 (Box 15)
  - A. Janet Dakin, Amherst, 1979 November 17 (Box 15)
  - A. Lillian Gish, N.Y.C., 1979 June 22 (Box 15)
  - A. Malcolm Cowley, Sherman, CT, 1980 April 14 (Box 15)
  - A. Mrs. Gilbert Chapman, Church Newton. B. W. Herbert Allen (Pasadena, Calif.), 1979-1980 (Box 16)
  - A. Paul Weiss, Washington D.C... B. Isabel Wilder, 1980 January (Box 16)
  - A. Sally Begley. B. Sally Begley, 1980 May 24; 3 (Box 16)
  - A. Samuel Steward... B. Mrs. Harold Kelley, Berkeley, Calif., 1980 January (Box 16)
  - A. Solof Faye Lesser, Los Angeles... B. Wm. Roenick, Bel-Air, California, 1979 May (Box 16)
  - A. Tappy Wilder, Washington D.C., 1980 April 29 (Box 16)
  - A. Timothy Findley Re Thornton Wilder, 1981 October (Box 16)
  - A. Wm. Roenick, Emmett Lavery... B. BLANK, 1979 May (Box 16)
- Correspondence, 1956-1985; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Series III, Correspondence, contains letters relating to Harrison's research project on Wilder. Letters between Harrison and others date chiefly from the research project, from 1979 through 1983, with a few exceptions, including copies of third-party correspondence (enclosures).
  Additional correspondence relating to publication and reception of Harrison's biography can be found in Series IV. Writings.
  - "A" general, 1979-1985, undated (Box 17)
  - "B" general, 1979-1983, undated (Box 17)
  - "C" general, 1978-1982 (Box 17)
  - "D" general, 1979-1983 (Box 17)
  - Dakin, Janet Wilder, 1969-1982 (Box 17)
  - "E" - "F" general, 1979-1982 (Box 17)
  - "G" general, 1979-1982 (Box 17)
  - "H" general, 1979-1983 (Box 17)
  - "I" - "K" general, 1979-1981, undated (Box 17)
  - "L" general, 1979-1983, undated (Box 17)
  - "M" general, 1979-1982, undated (Box 17)
  - "N" general, 1975-1982, undated (Box 17)
  - "O" - "R" general, 1979-1982, undated (Box 17)
  - "S" general, 1979-1982, undated (Box 17)
  - "U" - "V" general, 1979-1982, undated (Box 17)
  - "W" general, 1979-1981, undated (Box 17)
  - Wilder, Amos Niven, 1979-1982 (Box 17)
  - Wilder, Isabel, 1956-1982; 3 (Box 17)
    Includes copies of third-party correspondence between Isabel Wilder and others dating from 1961 to 1981
  - Wilder, Thornton, undated; 2 (Box 17)
    Contains copies of third-party correspondence dating from 1935 to 1975
  - Others, 1979-1982, undated; 2 (Box 17)
- Writings, 1980-1984; Series IV; 1.04; (3 boxes)
  Arranged in order of the creative process.
  Series IV, Writings, consists of correspondence, a corrected draft, and reviews relating to Harrison's biography of Thornton Wilder, The Enthusiast: A Life of Thornton Wilder. The correspondence contains letters with his literary agent, Brandt & Brandt, and publisher, Ticknor & Fields, documenting production of the book, and fan mail. The fan mail and reviews document critical reception of the book.
  - The Enthusiast: A Life of Thornton Wilder
    - Correspondence, 1980-1984; 3 (Box 18)
    - Draft, typescript, corrected, undated; 5 (Box 18)
    - Draft, typescript, corrected, undated; 5 (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous pages, undated (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous pages, undated; 2 (Box 20)
    - Book jacket, [circa 1983] (Box 20)
    - Reviews, 1983-1984; 3 (Box 20)
- Other Papers, 1984, undated; Series V; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series V, Other Papers, contains biographical information on Thornton and other Wilder family members, a copy of Wilder's 1967 will and testament, and photographs. Photographs include individual portraits and snapshots of Wilder and several images of Wilder with political and cultural figures, including Eleanor Lansing Dulles, Willi Brandt, and Ethel Waters, at the opening of Congress Hall in Berlin in 1957.
  - Biographical information, undated (Box 21)
  - Legal documents, undated (Box 21)
  - Photographs, 1984, undated (Box 21)